Ekaterina Lobacheva

Home page / Google Scholar / GitHub / Twitter

e-mail: lobacheva.tjulja@gmail.com tel: +1 438-365-3056

I'm a deep learning researcher mainly focusing on understanding the properties of neural network training and how they affect learned data representations and model generalization. I am also interested in ensemble and model-averaging methods, properties of neural network loss landscape, and specifics of training dynamics and representation learning in various training paradigms, such as self-supervised, transfer, continuous and online learning. The results of my work were published at top-tier conferences, including NeurIPS, AAAI, EMNLP, ICCV. Currently, I am a postdoc at Mila and Université de Montréal, working with Nicolas Le Roux and Irina Rish.

*denotes equal contribution	
To Stay or Not to Stay in the Pre-train Basin: Insights on Ensembling in Transfer L NeurIPS 2023 Ildus Sadrtdinov*, Dmitrii Pozdeev*, Dmitry Vetrov, Ekaterina Lobacheva	earning, paper / code
Training Scale-Invariant Neural Networks on the Sphere Can Happen in Three Reg NeurIPS 2022 Maxim Kodryan*, Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Maksim Nakhodnov*, Dmitry Vetrov	gimes, paper / code
On the Periodic Behavior of Neural Network Training with Batch Normalization and Decay, NeurIPS 2021 Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Maxim Kodryan*, Nadezhda Chirkova, Andrey Malinin, Dmitry	
On Power Laws in Deep Ensembles, NeurIPS 2020 (Spotlight) Ekaterina Lobacheva, Nadezhda Chirkova, Maxim Kodryan, Dmitry Vetrov	paper / code
Structured Sparsification of Gated Recurrent Neural Networks, AAAI 2020 (Oral) Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Nadezhda Chirkova*, Alexander Markovich, Dmitry Vetrov	paper / code
Bayesian Compression for Natural Language Processing , EMNLP 2018 Nadezhda Chirkova*, Ekaterina Lobacheva *, Dmitry Vetrov	paper / code
SELECTED WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS AND PREPRINTS	
Where Do Large Learning Rates Lead Us? A Feature Learning Perspective, ICML 20 Ildus Sadrtdinov, Maxim Kodryan, Eduard Pokonechny, Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Dmitr	Pupor
Gradient Dissent in Language Model Training and Saturation , ICML 2024 HiLD Andrei Mircea, Ekaterina Lobacheva , Irina Rish	paper
Large Learning Rates Improve Generalization: But How Large Are We Talking About NeurIPS 2023 M3L Workshop Ekaterina Lobacheva*, Eduard Pockonechnyy*, Maxim Kodryan, Dmitry Vetrov	paper
On the Memorization Properties of Contrastive Learning, ICML 2021 OPPO Workshildus Sadrtdinov, Nadezhda Chirkova, Ekaterina Lobacheva	nop paper
Deep Ensembles on a Fixed Memory Budget: One Wide Network or Several Thinner Nadezhda Chirkova, Ekaterina Lobacheva, Dmitry Vetrov	r Ones?, 2020 paper
Monotonic models for real-time dynamic malware detection, ICLR Workshop 2018 Alexander Chistyakov, Ekaterina Lobacheva, Alexander Shevelev, Alexey Romanenko	paper

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2024 - now Postdoctoral Research Fellow, Mila Quebec AI Institute and Université de Montréal

My current projects are focused on the effects of optimization methods and hyperparameters on the properties of the resulting trained network, gradient opposition and its impact on training of large foundational models, and analysis of loss landscape properties in transfer, continuous and multi-task learning. Advisors: Nicolas Le Roux and Irina Rish.

2023 - 2024 Independent Researcher

I led projects on ensembling in transfer learning setup and effects of large initial learning rate on network training, collaborating closely with researchers from Bayesian Methods Research Group. I also investigated neural network training trajectories in the function space and related generalization metrics in collaboration with Nicolas Le Roux.

2020 - 2022 Research Fellow and Deputy Head, Centre of Deep Learning and Bayesian Methods, HSE University

My research primarily focused on understanding the properties of neural networks training and loss landscape. Specifically, I investigated sharp and flat optima, mode connectivity, ensembling methods and the effects of normalization layers on training dynamics. The results were published at NeurIPS. As Deputy Head, I contributed to the organization and management of the lab.

2018 - 2020 Research Fellow, Samsung-HSE Laboratory at HSE University

I worked on Bayesian sparsification methods for recurrent neural networks, including techniques for embedding layers and gated layers such as LSTMs. The findings were published at EMNLP and AAAI.

2015 - 2018 Junior Researcher, Kaspersky Lab

I focused on feature extraction techniques and classification models for dynamic malware detection. The results were published at ICLR Workshops and built into the company's antivirus products.

Summer 2014

Research Intern, University of Western Ontario

I contributed to improving energy-based segmentation methods for camouflage images. The results were published at ICCV. Advisors: Yuri Boykov and Olga Veksler

EDUCATION

2022 **PhD** in Computer Science, **HSE University**

Thesis on: Deep learning architectures on a fixed memory budget Advisor: Dmitry Vetrov

Cum Laude

2009 - 2014 Specialist degree (BSc+MSc) in Computer Science, Lomonosov Moscow State University

Thesis on: Boltzmann machines for image segmentation Advisor: Dmitry Vetrov

Graduated with honors (GPA 5.0 out of 5.0)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- I mostly program in **Python** and my primary deep learning framework is **PyTorch**
- I am proficient with common data science tools such as NumPy, matplotlib, scikit-learn, pandas
- I'm comfortable with the common data science environment, including bash, git, Linux, GPU clusters

SELECTED THESIS SUPERVISION AND CO-SUPERVISION

- Ildus Sadrtdinov (currently a PhD student at HSE University)
 - On the Memorization Properties of Contrastive Learning (BSc, 2021)
 - Ensembling Neural Networks in the Transfer Learning Setup (MSc, 2023)
- Sergey Troshin (currently a PhD student at University of Amsterdam)
 - Deep Equilibrium ResNet (BSc, 2020)

- Maksim Ryabinin (PhD, currently a Distinguished Research Scientist at Together AI)
 - Gradient Optimization of Beam Search Hyperparameters (BSc, 2019)
- Polina Kirichenko (PhD, currently a Research Scientist at Meta AI)
 - Study of Bayesian Regularization of Neural Networks (BSc, 2018)
- Nadezhda Chirkova (PhD, currently a Research Scientist at Naver Labs)
 - Bayesian Compression for Natural Language Processing, (MSc, 2018)

TEACHING

2016 - 2024	Research seminar Machine Learning and Applications, Faculty of Computer Science at HSE University
2015 - 2021	Bayesian Methods in Machine Learning (organization + practical sessions) , HSE University, MSU, and Yandex School of Data Analysis
2018 - 2019	Neurobayesian models (organization + practical sessions), HSE University, MSU, and Yandex School of Data Analysis
2017	Introduction to Deep Learning (Online course at Coursera, lectures)
2016 - 2017	Deep learning (lectures and practical sessions), MSU
2016 - 2017	Machine learning (lectures), HSE and HSE/NES Programmes in Economics
2015 - 2017	Data analysis (practical sessions), HSE University

Additionally, I was one of the main organizers and gave several lectures at the Deep|Bayes Summer School from 2017 to 2019. Together with Nadezhda Chirkova, I also led a tutorial on Bayesian machine learning at the Machine Learning in High Energy Physics Summer School (Hamburg, Germany, July 2019 and online, July 2020 and 2021), as well as at the Workshop on Machine Learning and Applications to Physics (Madrid, Spain, Dec 2019).

PROGRAM COMMITTEE

Neural Information Processing Systems, NeurIPS (reviewer):

- 2019: top-50% highest-scored reviewer
- 2021: outstanding reviewer award (top-8%)
- 2023: top reviewer